Good morning, יום שישי. Yom Shishi.
Today's דף Daf is כ"ג. Chaf Gimmel. We pick up at the
bottom of כ"ב עמוד ב'. Chaf Bais Amud Bais. We have this
very large משנה, Mishnah, which is all about when you say a
חטאת Chatas that the owner was נתכפר באחר, niskaper b'acher, was lost
and they were atoned with through another one, when it's מתה. mesa.
According to the חכמים, Chachamim, it's only if they found the missing
one after they were already atoned with the other one. And according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's even if they found the missing
one after they just was sanctified the second one. And the גמרא
Gemara is going to deal with the fact that the beginning of
the משנה Mishnah was like the חכמים Chachamim and it says when
it was actually, actually they הקריב, hikriv, they brought the second one.
And then the middle of the משנה Mishnah deals all with implicitly
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because it talks about solutions that if you
can get the moneys to comingle, then you don't have to designate
one that you brought and the other that you didn't bring. But
that would only be in a case when you found the missing
one or the missing money before the atonement. So how is it
that the beginning is the Rabbis and the middle is רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara now five lines from the bottom or so, six lines
from the bottom on כ"ב עמוד ב'. Chaf Bais Amud Bais. טעמא
דהקריב אחרת תחתיה. Ta'ama de'hikriv acheres tachata.
The first line of the משנה Mishnah says, why does the second
one have to die? Because when you found it, you had already
brought the, why does the first one have to die? It says
because when you found it, you had already brought the second one
in its stead. הא לא הקריב אחרת תחתיה, Ha lo hikriv acheres
tachata,
if you hadn't already brought the second one and it's dead, it
was just sanctified, רועה, ro'eh, then it would graze. מני רבנן היא,
Mani Rabbanan hi, that's the רבנן Rabbanan דאמרי אבודה בשעת הפרשה רועה,
d'amri avuda b'sha'as hafrasha ro'eh, even if it was lost, meaning and
found really, at the time when it was designated and it was
not still lost at the time when the other one was brought,
it was only lost when the other one was sanctified, then it
does not die, it grazes.
Is this a מפריש חטאת ואבדה mafrish chatas v'avda case?
No, the first line of the משנה, Mishnah, מפריש חטאת ואבדה, mafrish
chatas v'avda, and that's why the text has to be והקריב, v'hikriv,
not ואבדה, v'avda, I
mean because our text says...
yeah, that's why the text has switched to והקריב, v'hikriv, that's implicitly
what the גמרא Gemara has. Okay. So the first line of the
משנה Mishnah says only if the first one is brought after the
second is brought. But if it's found before only after the second
is sanctified, it's not, it'll graze, it won't die. So that's the
position of the רבנן. Rabbanan. Then it says, אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
let's look at the end, really like the middle of the משנה.
Mishnah. המפריש מעות לחטאת ואבדו, Ha'mafrish ma'os l'chatas v'avdu, you designated that
money, they got lost, והביא אחרים תחתיהם, v'hivia acherim tachteihem, and then
you designated out another pile of money or sanctified, and then you
found the first pile. How do you solve it from not being
a case that one of them has to be thrown into the
ים המלח? Yam Hamelach? יביא מאלו ומאלו. Yavi me'elu u'me'elu. Bring the,
you buy the חטאת chatas from both piles, not just from one
pile, and therefore it's all considered there's no one pile that it
was the chosen and the other that was the rejected. And therefore
the rest of the money is just leftover money, ושאר יפלו לנדבה,
v'sha'ar yiplu l'nedava, and you use that to bring an עולה. olah.
So therefore you see that's a scenario where you found the missing
one before the second one was brought. And the only way you
solve the problem is by mixing the moneys. It's not, so the
very fact that it was found before the second was brought is
not enough to save the day. So טעמא מאלו ומאלו, ta'ama me'elu
u'me'elu, the way that that has solved the problem is because you
bring the חטאת chatas from both of the moneys. הא הביא מאחד
מהן, Ha heivi me'echad meihen, if you bought the חטאת chatas just
from one pile of money, השני יוליכו לים המלח, hasheini yolichu l'Yam
Hamelach, the second pile has to be thrown out, have to be
thrown into the Dead Sea. So you see אזלן לרבי, aslan l'Rabbi,
that's going like רבי Rabbi דאמר אבודה בשעת הפרשה
מתה, d'amar avuda b'sha'as hafrasha mesa, that even if it was only
lost when the second one was sanctified, even if it was found
before the second one was brought, you still say that it has
to die because the only solution here is to mix the money.
So it sounds like fundamentally there's a problem even if it's found
before the הקרבה. hakrava. רישא רבנן וסיפא רבי? Reisha Rabbanan v'seifa Rabbi?
How could it be that the first line is the רבנן Rabbanan
and the second line is רבי? Rabbi? Okay, now we're going to
introduce that there are two Amoraic approaches that limit the רבנן Rabbanan
and based on the way they limit the רבנן, Rabbanan, maybe that's
a way to have it all be according to the רבנן. Rabbanan.
Okay, that sometimes the Rabbis, the argument will be sometimes the רבנן
Rabbanan will agree with רבי Rabbi that even if it's found before
the second one is brought, it still has to die. Now you
might remember, and I don't want to confuse because it was a
confusing דף, daf, but you might remember yesterday we had all that
issue about being lost and having a מום, mum, being lost and
being a... more than a year old. And the way רש"י Rashi
read that was רש"י Rashi read that as there are some cases
where the רבנן Rabbanan will agree to רבי Rabbi that even if
it's found before the second is brought, if it's got some other
problems, it also will have to die. So in that vein, we
are going to see here two Amoraic approaches that say the same
thing, that there are times where the רבנן Rabbanan will agree to
רבי Rabbi that even if found before the second is brought, it
might be it will have to die. Let's take a look. הא
ניחא לרב הונא, Ha nicha l'Rav Huna, that it works according to
רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, D'amar Rav Huna
amar Rav, because רב הונא Rav Huna said in the name of
רב, Rav, top of כ"ג עמוד א', Chaf Gimmel Amud Aleph, הכל
מודים שאם נשתייר והקריבה, hakol modim she'im nish'tayer v'hikriva,
everybody agrees that if you actually selected one, meaning you found the
first one before the second was brought, and you on your own
initiative selected one of them והקריבה, v'hikriva, ששנייה מתה, she'shniya mesa, that
it does die. Meaning basically the רבנן Rabbanan agree to רבי Rabbi
that if you go ahead and you found one of them and
then you found the missing one and then you selected one, the
second one dies. So they agree
to, what's the debate? So the debate is, and this is very
interesting, the גמרא Gemara will spell it out in a minute, when
you actually... go to בית דין. Beis Din. Now what we have
to understand is there are two things here that the גמרא Gemara
is assuming makes a difference. Number one, and this actually came up
in some back and forth Michael and I had over the last
day or so, is that logically you would say when you find
the missing one, assuming that you have not yet brought the other
one, right when you find the missing one, you would think it
might matter which one you're now going to bring as a קרבן.
korban. Right, if you bring the second one you sanctified, then there
may be more reason to say that this should מתה meisa because
it was missing, it was, it was like rejected, it was lost
and so on. Right, if you bring the missing one, the one
that had been missing as a קרבן, korban, then this one was
never so bad, it was already, always sort of designated, always fit
to be brought. So maybe it wouldn't be מתה. meisa. Maybe it
would only be מתה meisa if you bring the second one, right
understand? Because the first one had actually been lost and out of
the picture and maybe that's a reason for greater rejection. So that's
assumption number one actually is true. Whatever reason for the rabbis to
agree to רבי Rebbe when it was found before it was brought,
there's more of a reason to agree if you actually bring the
second and that the first one is because that since that was
rejected to begin with, that remains sort of מתה. meisa. That's going
to be one approach that's basically going to say
even without the don't think anyone knows all that.
Right, but just the fact that it was מתה meisa when you
sanctified the other, you had already sort of chosen another over it.
So that's going to be one approach that says the rabbis will
agree to רבי Rebbe if you bring the second one, that the
first one has to die. Now this approach sort of builds on
that and this approach says
that
there's another way in which you increase the sense of sort of
like rejection. And how do you increase the sense of rejection is
when you on your own initiative say I'm picking A and I'm
not picking B. Then it's like oh, you're rejecting B. So therefore
even the rabbis would agree it's מתה. meisa. But if you basically
go to בית דין Beis Din and say to בית דין, Beis
Din, I really want to solve this solution, I really would like
to bring both if I could, what can I do here to
make this work? So you're not basically saying alright I like this
one and I don't like that one. You're sort of, you're trying
to make it work. So if you're trying to make it work,
then the בית דין Beis Din will advise you to bring the
one that had been lost because you're bringing the one that had
been lost, therefore the other one which was never so bad doesn't
have to die. So then you wait for it a moment and
you bring it as an עולה. olah. So this, the approach is
basically, I mean I'm making it a little more complicated than what's
presented here because it'll become more, it'll get to that level of
complexity in a few minutes, I wanted to prepare you for it.
But basically the point here is, is that the rabbis will agree
to רבי Rebbe if you selected it on your own. That that's
a rejection. But if you actually go to the rabbis or בית
דין Beis Din and ask what you should do, that's when the
rabbis will say ah, then bring the one that was lost and
the other one just has to graze. So their only debate of
רבי Rebbe is in this special case where you ask their opinion
and they told you to bring the one that was lost because
the other one is never so bad because it was never lost.
Okay, so wait, so you said in the first case where you
didn't ask the rabbis and you go and you mark the second
one, then the first one dies, right?
But if you didn't ask the rabbis regardless of which one you
pick, you're by virtue of picking one you're rejecting the other.
So then the other one dies.
And the other, and in theory,
so basically everyone agrees to that.
Everyone. So this approach right really limits the debate of the rabbis
and רבי Rebbe and basically says the חכמים Chachamim only say that
it doesn't have to die if you ask their opinion and then
they advise you which one to take. Okay, so let's take a
look. So according to that, משכחת לה, meshkachat lah, then I can
understand that most of the משנה Mishnah is even the רבנן. Rabbanan.
How is most of the
משנה Mishnah רבנן? Rabbanan? דגזל ושמשך אחת מהן והקריב ודמי הפקדון. d'gazal
u'she'mashach achas meihen v'hikriv v'damei ha'pikadon. That basically the middle part of
the משנה Mishnah is that you weren't asking the rabbis. Since you
weren't asking the rabbis, if you had just taken one of the
piles of money, then the other one would have had to be
thrown out because you didn't ask the rabbis. But if you were
smart enough to realize or you're a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and
you had read the משנה, Mishnah, you were smart enough to realize
that you could mix the piles together, then you could solve the
problem without going to the rabbis. Okay, so the middle case of
the משנה Mishnah which said that you would have to actually throw
them into ים המלח, Yam HaMelach, how does that work according to
the חכמים? Chachamim? Right, if you found it before you brought the
second one, it works because you didn't ask the rabbis and in
that case the חכמים Chachamim would agree to רבי. Rebbe. But if
even without asking the rabbis you knew how to mix the piles
together,
then you can solve the problem without asking the rabbis. Now of
course it raises the question,
what if you're the same תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and you know
that if I ask the rabbis, you know what the rabbis are
going to tell you? It still seems like if you're תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham enough to know that you can mix the money, but
it still, but you, it doesn't matter that you know the הלכה.
halacha. It seems according to this approach that you have to actually
go and ask the rabbis to show that you are not choosing
one over the other, that you are trying to sort of make
the best of the circumstances. So that's the way of reading it.
It's according to the approach if, if, according to the approach the
חכמים Chachamim agree to רבי Rebbe when you do it on your
own. The whole משנה Mishnah is that you did it on your
own. If you picked one pile, you're in trouble. If you mix
the piles, you're okay. But if you would ask the rabbis, then
there are other solutions.
If you just clarify, you have two animals and then you have
this money. How, what was the connection?
No, so the cases in the middle were cases where you weren't
dealing with animals, where you were dealing with money. You picked out
a pile and you said it got lost and you designated
another pile and then you found it. And the other thing is
when you graze it and it gets a מום, mum, is that
called redemption when you sell it or you just sell it and
then you buy an עולה? olah?
No, that is called redemption.
It is for redemption. Yeah, okay.
Okay, so now the משנה mishna so that makes sense then the
חכמים chachamim agree to רבי Rebbe when you did it on your
own so the whole משנה mishna could be when you did it
on your own. אלא לרבי אבא דאמר רב דאמר הכל מודים
במתכפר בשאינה אבודה שאבודה מתה Ella l'Rebbe Abba d'amar Rav d'amar hakol
modim b'miskapeir b'she'eina avuda she'avuda meisa by this it's a simpler case
to understand. Even the חכמים chachamim agree to רבי Rebbe that if
you use the if you use number two that number one has
to מתה. meisa. Because number one was the one that was lost
so it already is stigmatized. So if you went ahead and you
were מקדיש makdish number two even if you found number one before
number number one has to מתה. meisa. So that they agree to
when you use number two.
On your own.
On your own. This approach doesn't distinguish on your own or בית
דין. beis din. It's all a question of which one you use.
If you use number two even חכמים chachamim agree number one has
to מתה. meisa. על מה נחלקו? Al mah nechloku? What's the debate?
במתכפר באבודה. B'miskapeir b'avuda. You found number one and you used number
one. So the חכמים chachamim would say oh that's okay because even
though the one that was lost you know wasn't the one that
was now rejected. The one that was rejected wasn't lost so it's
not so bad. So רבי Rebbe סבר savar nevertheless רבי Rebbe holds
מפריש כאיבוד כאיבוד דמי. maphrish k'ibud k'ibud dami. Since when you designated
number two it was to stand instead of number one it has
the same status as number one. So the same way number one
has a status of lost number two has a quasi status of
lost because it's coming instead of number one. So therefore the same
way number one would be if you picked number two number one
would be מתה meisa if you picked number one number two is
מתה meisa because number two has the exact same הלכה halacha as
number one. רבי Rebbe סבר כאיבוד דמי savar k'ibud dami רבנן סברי
לאו כאיבוד דמי. rabbanan savri lav k'ibud dami. No number two was
never lost number two is a totally fine animal so therefore the
rabbis say if you bring number one as a קרבן korban number
two never had a problem.
It was never it never had the status of lost so therefore
it's not מתה. meisa. Okay so anyway that makes a lot of
sense that the whole debate is when you bring number number number
one but if you bring number two everybody agrees since number one
had been lost it remains מתה. meisa. In that case in that
case how do you explain the משנה? mishna? Because the whole משנה
mishna says that when you found missing piles of money the only
way to solve it was by mixing the moneys. But according to
this approach there's another way to solve it. Just make sure you
bring the חטאת chatas from the missing pile of money right? Because
according to this the חכמים chachamim would say that if you're if
you use what had been missing you salvage the situation you wouldn't
have to actually mix it. So we're back to our question. How
could the beginning be the חכמים? chachamim? Because it says only after
it was brought and the middle seems like רבי Rebbe because the
middle says the only way to salvage it is by mixing the
money but according to this you can salvage it by just bringing
the pile of money that had been lost. So the גמרא Gemara
says basically and the שיטה shita here which is the גרסא girsa
a little אין in רישא רבנן וסיפא רבי. reisha rabbanan v'seifa Rebbe.
Okay big deal fine. The first line was the
rabbis then it got onto elaborating רבי's Rebbe position. ומאי קמשמע לן?
U'mai kamashmalan? So what's it tell me? דפליגי רבי ורבנן. D'pligi Rebbe
v'rabbanan. So it wants to tell me that there's a debate of
רבי Rebbe and רבנן. rabbanan. So why did it have to say
it by spelling out these cases? Bottom line it tells me it
very clearly. בהדיא קתני לה מחלוקת רבי ורבנן בסיפא B'hedya katani la
machlokes Rebbe v'rabbanan b'seifa it says explicitly at the end.
המפריש חטאת ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה Hamaphrish chatas v'avda v'hiphrish acheres tachteha
you designated a חטאת chatas it got lost and then you designated
another one. ואחר כך נמצאת הראשונה V'acharkach nimtza harishona and you found
the first one before you had brought the second. והרי שתיהן עומדות
אחת מהן
תקרב ושניה תמות דברי רבי. V'harei shteihen omudos achas meihen tikrav v'shniya
tamus divrei Rebbe. רבי Rebbe says bring one of the קרבן korban
the other one will die. וחכמים אומרים אין חטאת מתה אלא אם
כן נמצאת לאחר שכיפרו הבעלים. V'chachamim omrim ein chatas meisa ela im
ken nimtza l'achar shekiperu habaalim. No only if you find it after
the owners were atoned for. ואין מעות הולכות לים המלח אלא אם
כן נמצאו לאחר שכיפרו הבעלים. V'ein maos holchos l'yam hamelach ela im
ken nimtzu l'achar shekiperu habaalim. And also the money is only a
problem after they were atoned for. So we very explicitly state the
מחלוקת machlokes there. Why do we in the first half of the
משנה mishna implicitly have their different positions without if we're going to
explicitly say it at the
end? So the גמרא Gemara says הא קמשמע לן דבר זה מחלוקת
רבי ורבנן. Ha kamashmalan davar zeh machlokes Rebbe v'rabbanan. Fine. First it's
giving me different שיטות shitos and then it says by the way
you should know that the issue we discussed are dependent on a
debate of רבי Rebbe and רבנן. rabbanan. The really the reason that
it should spell it out is because it's interesting the first half
of the משנה. mishna. It tells me this idea of mixing the
money. I never would have realized this idea of mixing the money.
So that really seems to be what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
That first we say the חכמים chachamim שיטה shita then we spell
out this interesting הלכה halacha according to רבי Rebbe of mixing the
money that רבי Rebbe if you find it even before you're atoned
you've got a problem. But if it's all money there's a solution
or you can make it all money there's a solution of mixing
the money. And then it says by the way be aware that
this is really debated between רבי Rebbe and the רבנן. rabbanan. Because
according to the רבנן rabbanan if you found it before you brought
the other one you wouldn't have a problem anyway for them they
only have a problem if you find it after you were atoned
for. Okay so that we've explained now the משנה mishna but now
we've also seen that there's times where the חכמים chachamim might agree
to רבי Rebbe and now we're going to look at that a
little bit more closely. Let's take a look. גופא. Gufa. אמר רב
הונא אמר רב הכל מודים שאם משך אחת והקריבה ששניה מתה. Amar
Rav Huna amar Rav hakol modim she'im mashach achas v'hikriva she'shniya meisa.
Everybody agrees that
if you selected one on your own you found it before the
second number two was brought and you selected it on your own.
That's essentially you've rejected one then everybody agrees that it has to
מתה. meisa. לא נחלקו אלא בבא לימלך. Lo nechloku ela b'ba l'imalech.
The only debate is when you came to ask בית דין beis
din what should I do. שרבי סבר לא עשו תקנה בקדשים. SheRebbe
savar lo asu takana b'kodshim. We are not going to try to
fix up the case which is a shocking position basically it's like
you know like
we don't really care. תוספות Tosfos states, well, let's read it and
then I'll read you what תוספות Tosfos says about this. We're not
going to try to solve the situation. ורמינהו, U'reminhu, and we say
לכי כפר באבודה, lechi kaper ba'avuda, go, you know, skip the line.
ורמינהו לכי כפר בשאינה אבודה, U'reminhu lechi kaper beshe'eina avuda, go bring
number two as a קרבן, korban, ואבודה תמות, va'avuda tamus, and number
one, which had been lost, already had a stigmatized status, let it
die, what do we care? ורבנן סברי, Verabbanan savri, and the rabbis
hold, עשו תקנה בקדשים, asu takana bekodshim, no, we're going to try
to salvage the situation. ורמינהו ואימא, U'reminhu ve'eima, and we say, לכי
כפר באבודה, lechi kaper ba'avuda, go use number one, because if you're
using number one, that was the only one that was lost, so
if you use that one now, then number two won't be, was
never stigmatized, so you can salvage number two. So go use number
one, that was the one that was lost,
ושאינה אבודה תרעה, veshe'eina avuda tireh, and number two, which had never
been lost, so even though it wasn't brought now as a קרבן,
korban, that will be allowed to graze. Okay, so here's where you
see, this is what I was introducing to you before, that there
are two considerations, meaning number one is,
if you made the selection on your own, you automatically, it doesn't
matter whether you picked number one or number two, by virtue of
making the selection on your own, you're rejecting one of them, and
that gives it a status of תמות. tamus. If you go to
בית דין, Beis Din, then it's not going to be translated as
a rejection. Okay, but so therefore the חכמים Chachamim say, ah, so
therefore if you use the one as a קרבן korban that wasn't
lost, that was lost, and the one that wasn't lost never got
stigmatized, so you salvaged it. ורבי VeRebbi fundamentally agrees that that would
be true if you were to bring number, number one, you would
salvage number two, but he's not interested in salvaging the situation. So
he says bring number two and let number one die. Which is,
that's what you should do, which is totally bizarre, right? So let's
take a look at תוספות Tosfos that says, what does this mean
that רבי Rebbi doesn't care to try to salvage the situation? So
דרבי סבר לא עשו תקנה בקדשים, deRebbi savar lo asu takana bekodshim,
look at this תוספות. Tosfos. תימא למורי הרב ר', Teima leMori haRav
R', whoever that is, הרמ"ר, haRamar, I don't even know who that
refers to, וכי מאבדין קדשים בידיים, vechi ma'avdin kodshim beyadayim, כיון דבידו
לתקן, keivan deyado letaken, you have a solution, why is רבי Rebbi
not trying to salvage it, why is he letting this animal die?
ותרץ דכאן שיש רווח בדבר, viteretz dekan sheyesh revach badavar, כגון דאבודה
כחושה ושאינה אבודה שמינה, kegon de'avuda kchusha veshe'eina avuda shmeina, ואמר ליה,
ve'amar lei,
so he says there's some benefit, for example, if you use number,
number two, you're bringing a nicer קרבן korban to the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. התכפר בטובה והכחושה תמות. hiskaper betova vehakchusha tamus.
So he's more interested, alright, so then he basically is answering אין
הכי נמי, in hachi nami, it's very strange that the גמרא Gemara
just says it without any qualification. תוספות Tosfos tries to soften it
a little bit, that רבי Rebbi basically says, I'm not concerned, I'm
not, I'm not trying to
be going to be concerned with helping you, you know, you got
yourself into the situation, I'm not going to try to help you.
If it's to the benefit of הקדש, hekdesh, I'm going to say
select number two and let number one, and let number one die.
Okay, but anyway, that becomes now a very interesting new qualification. On
the one hand, in theory רבי Rebbi would agree that there is
a way to salvage it, if you were to ask בית דין
Beis Din and בית דין Beis Din would tell you bring number
one, but רבי Rebbi isn't interested in telling you that. And also
that the חכמים Chachamim agree in most cases to רבי, Rebbi, if
you select it by yourself, it's rejecting it, the only way you
salvage it is by bringing it to בית דין Beis Din and
only there, only by them telling you bring number one, and therefore
number two can be salvaged, because number two was never lost, so
it can be
salvaged. Okay, is
that
clear? Okay, alright. So, alright, yeah, it's all so
simple, anyway, so let's say, I'm purely teasing for
marketing purposes. Okay, okay, מתיב רב משרשיא, Masiv Rav Mesharshiya, okay, so
now, now before we get onto the other opinion, we're going to
challenge this idea that they didn't try to salvage the case according
to רבי, Rebbi, they don't try to salvage
things. So מתיב רב משרשיא, Masiv Rav Mesharshiya, לא עשו תקנה בקדשים,
lo asu takana bekodshim, are they, we not trying to salvage this
situation by קדשים kodshim according to רבי? Rebbi? והתניא, Vehatanya, יאכלו, yochlu,
we have a ברייתא braisa that says they shall eat it. מאי
טעמא דקרא, Mai ta'ama dekra, this is talking about the eating of
the, excuse me, what am I
trying to remember what's it talking about? Oh yes, the remainder of
the מנחה. mincha. So it says יאכלו, yochlu, it says in the,
in the area of the משכן, Mishkan, in the yard of the
משכן, Mishkan, they shall eat it. So that was an extra word,
because it said eat earlier in the verse. So מאי טעמא דקרא,
mai ta'ama dekra, why is it saying this by the remnant of
the
מנחה mincha
that
the כהנים... Kohanim... of מנחות Minchos and maybe a lot of כהנים.
Kohanim. So the idea is you're supposed to eat קרבנות Korbanos not
when you're ravenous or but when you are relatively full so that
it's like you're not eating it out of hunger, you're eating it
because you like desire, like dessert, right? So therefore you're supposed to
be relatively full before you eat קרבנות. Korbanos. Okay, פשט, Peshat, but
it's really true about all קרבנות Korbanos supposed to be על השובע.
al hasova.
Really? Even שלמים? Shelamim?
More or less. Anyway, well that's interesting. Would it apply by the
אכילת בעלים? achilas be'alim? Primarily say this by אכילת כהנים, achilas Kohanim,
so I'm not sure. I'll have to get back to you. Alright,
so anyway, so we say if there's only a little מנחה Mincha
and a lot of כהנים, Kohanim, then go ahead and eat before,
and then when you eat it, you'll be relatively full. Now רש"י
Rashi asks a question. He says how can you be eating
non-קדשים Kodashim in the
בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? In the עזרה? Azara? You're not supposed to
bring חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azara. So רש"י Rashi says fine, go outside,
go to a restaurant, then you come back. But I will say
that תוספות Tosafos in other places actually says, let me just see
if he says it here. Yeah, תוספות Tosafos here says אוכלין עמה
חולין ותרומה, ochlin imah chullin u-trumah, the middle of that
תוספות Tosafos says, ועוד יש לומר דאין איסור להכניס חולין בעזרה כל
שאינו עושה שום עבודה מהם. Ve-od yesh lomar de-ein issur lehachnis chullin
ba-azara kol she-eino oseh shum avodah me-hem. תוספות Tosafos generally says there's
no prohibition of bringing things that are not קדשים Kodashim into the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. There's a prohibition of treating them like קדשים,
Kodashim, of doing pseudo-עבודות avodos with them and so on, but just
having my steak in
there if I want,
in theory, whether it's necessarily respectful for you to eat it there,
but that's not the problem of חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azara. So if
the כהנים Kohanim are doing it for the sake of that the
way they eat the מנחה Mincha should be appropriate, so תוספות Tosafos
would say that would be okay. Okay,
צריכין שק.
Tzerichin shak. Yeah, I've been hearing for years about how we can't
take חולין chullin into the עזרה. Azara.
But look at the end of תוספות, Tosafos, it says דהא כמה
דאדם נכנס בבגדי חולין בעזרה. de-ha kama de-adam nichnas be-vigdei chullin ba-azara.
How about your clothes? Right? So there are a lot of things
that are not sanctified. Okay, now you could ask is it appropriate
to eat in the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? But anyway, we're talking
about the כהנים Kohanim eating for the purpose of עבודה. avodah. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says like this. Okay,
יאכלוה. Yochluha. So how do you get, how do you get that
from יאכלוה? Yochluha? That there should be an extra eating that should
be done for the sake of the מנחה. Mincha. You should eat
it. מה תלמוד לומר? Ma talmud lomar? שאם היתה אכילה מרובה, she-im
haysa achila meruba, that if there is a lot of מנחות Minchos
and not too many כהנים, Kohanim, so אין אוכלין עמה חולין ותרומה.
ein ochlin imah chullin u-trumah. Then we tell you don't eat before
it's time to eat the מנחה, Mincha, כדי שלא תהא נאכלת על
אכילה גסה, kedei she-lo tehai ne-echeles al achila gassa, so because then
you'll be stuffing yourself and that won't be a legitimate אכילה. achila.
So basically we want to ensure that all of it, that all
of it gets eaten. And therefore to ensure all of it gets
eaten, if there's a lot of food and not too many כהנים,
Kohanim, we say don't eat before it's time to eat the מנחה.
Mincha. So the גמרא Gemara says, so why is that relevant to
us? מאי לאו אפילו לרבי? Mai lav afilu le-Rabbi? Wouldn't that be
even רבי? Rabbi? That רבי Rabbi would basically agree that we should
advise people how to act in order to ensure that the קדשים
Kodashim get dealt with properly?
לא רבנן. Lo rabanan.
No, maybe it's only the רבנן. Rabanan. Maybe רבי Rabbi wouldn't care,
you do what you do, if you get yourself in a situation,
not our problem. Which is kind of shocking because this is, you
know, תוספות Tosafos at least before tried to soften it by saying,
well, if there's an interest for the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we're
not going to try to help you if the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash has to lose out. But here, you know, the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash is gaining no, I mean nobody is gaining by there
being extra stuff left over. So the idea that רבי Rabbi really
couldn't care about the תקנת קדשים takanas kodashim is a very strange
idea. Anyway, that's one approach, that really the issue is that the
חכמים Chachamim agree when you do it on your own initiative, and
when you have בית דין, Beis Din, then בית דין Beis Din
will advise you to take number one, but according to רבי, Rabbi,
it won't, בית דין Beis Din is not interested in giving you
that advice.
So why does תוספות Tosafos try to soften it if the גמרא
Gemara clearly doesn't care?
Because he's troubled, we're troubled. I don't know how he deals with
the continuation of the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
goes like this. רבי אבא אמר, Rabbi Abba amar, now we're back
to רבי אבא אמר רב, Rabbi Abba amar Rav, הכל מודים במתכפר
בשאינה אבודה שאבודה מתה. hakol modim be-miskaper be-she-eina avuda she-avuda mesa. Everybody
agrees that if you bring number two, that number one dies, because
number one was the lost one. And this הלכה halacha as we've
been saying about מתכפר באחר miskaper be-acher fundamentally is applied to something
that was lost. אמר נחלקו במתכפר באבודה, Amar nechelku be-miskaper be-avuda, that
when you brought the one that was lost, you had brought number
one as a קרבן. korban. So therefore number two had never been
lost. So maybe the whole הלכה halacha doesn't apply to number two.
דרבי סבר מוחלפת כקדושה דמי. De-Rabbi savar muchlefes ke-kedusha dami. רבי Rabbi
says no, since you designated number two to be in its, in
stead of number one, it has the same quality like number one
and it's quasi, it's sort of pseudo-lost. So therefore number two also
can become no good. ורבנן סברי לאו כקדושה דמי. Ve-rabanan savri lav
ke-kedusha dami. No, number two was never lost and therefore it will
never become no good. Okay, that's a very nice way of understanding
their debate. תנן השני ירעה עד שיסתאב וימכר ויביא בדמיו אחרים שאין
חטאת ציבור מתה. Tnan, hasheni yireh ad she-yista-ev ve-yimacher ve-yavi bi-damav acherim
she-ein chatas tzibbur mesa.
Remember we had this yesterday, when you went ahead and you had
the, one of the two goats of יום כיפור Yom Kippur died,
you have to bring a second pair, and what do you do,
and you know, in order to do the lots again, what do
you do with the extra goat? So you let it graze and
you use the money for an עולה olah because since it's חטאת
ציבור, chatas tzibbur, it's not מתה. mesa. So from that we're going.
infer, like we did yesterday, if it were a חטאת יחיד, Chatas
Yachid, it would be מתה. Mesa. So what does this tell us
of the הלכה Halacha when a חטאת יחיד Chatas Yachid dies? So
now, first of all, we have to understand which animal is being
brought, is it the which animal is grazing, is you know, is
not being brought, is it the one from the first pair or
the one from the second pair? So let's take a look. Yesterday
we took an opinion that it was the one from the first
pair that wasn't being brought. Here we're doing the other opinion. ואמר
רב Va'amar Rav and Rav says, I'm sorry, הא דיחיד מתה Ha
d'yachid mesa if it were an individual korban it would die. Now
which one is not being brought of these two pairs? ואמר רב
Va'amar Rav בעלי חיים אינם נדחים. Ba'alei chayim einam nidchim. If it's
a live animal, it never gets like rejected. So therefore when the
first pair, the animal that was designated as the חטאת, Chatas, the
one that didn't die, that remains valid. If it's alive, it doesn't
get rejected, it remains valid.
כשהוא מתכפר בשני שבזוג ראשון מתכפר. Keshehu miskaper besheini shebezug rishon miskaper.
So which one does he use? He uses the one that was
left over from the first pair, meaning the one he doesn't use
is the one from the second pair. ואידך בתרא. Ve'idach basra. So
the second one הוי ליה כהפריש לאיבוד. Havei lei kehafrish le'ibud. It's
like you're designating it for the one for the for the איבוד.
Ibud. What does that mean?
It's the only one we use anyway, so the other one is
you know.
Right. So it means that it means that when you go ahead
and so you're going to say that this second one here, it's
not such a clear analogy, right? Because the point in our case
was when you one was lost, you set designated a second one,
that second one was instead of the first, but it was actually
the one that you were planning on bringing, right? According to this
and therefore we could say, well, it's not considered like it's איבוד
Ibud because it's you're planning on bringing it, you know, it's not
lost. But here the analogy is not so good because here you're
going to use the goat from the first pair. You're creating a
second pair. So the goat here that's opposite the goat from the
first pair is מפריש לאיבוד Mafrish le'ibud it's corresponding to this one,
but it's sort of like the flip case. This is the one
that's going to be brought. This year's goat because you need to
do a ritual with the two, but you know all along that
this one is never going to be brought, right? So it's a
little bit it's not really analogous because in the other case you
were separating out and you were expecting to bring. Here you're separating
it out and you know you're not going to be able to
bring it.
Yes, so the first pair, one becomes a חטאת, Chatas, the other
goes to עזאזל. Azazel. And the one that's going to עזאזל Azazel
gets lost. So you have the second pair. Right. And you know
that neither of them are going to be.
No, no, no, the one that's going to be the חטאת Chatas
got lost.
Oh, the one that's
going to be the חטאת Chatas died, died, died, not got lost,
died. Right.
Okay, so so you're going to pick
your חטאת Chatas and your
עזאזל Azazel from the second pair. Right?
So you oh no, no, no, no, you were right, I'm sorry,
you were right, you were right.
The one I'm
sorry, you were right, the one that's going לעזאזל L'azazel dies. So
you have here the one that's going to be the חטאת Chatas
and you have two here.
Neither of you know neither which are going to be a חטאת.
Chatas.
Right. One will be the עזאזל Azazel and this one will correspond
to that but you're never going to use it. Right. So the
גמרא Gemara says this should be like מפריש לאיבוד Mafrish le'ibud and
why does it have to die according to the חכמים? Chachamim? But
the answer is that this is worse because this you knew wasn't
going to be used as opposed to when you sanctify number two,
you were planning on using it. But that's the comparison the גמרא
Gemara makes. So let's take a look.
Okay.
Yeah.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואידך בתרא הוי ליה כהפריש
לאיבוד וטעמא דציבור הא דיחיד מתה. Ve'idach basra havei lei kehafrish le'ibud
v'ta'ama d'tzibur ha d'yachid mesa. If it were an individual it dies.
מאי לאו רבנן? Mai lav rabanan? Isn't it even the רבנן? Rabanan?
So you see that even if you're מפריש לאיבוד Mafrish le'ibud it
that when you're מפריש לאיבוד Mafrish le'ibud or whatever, anyway, it does
get that status and it does become a problem of מתה. Mesa.
לא רבי היא. Lo Rabi hi. No, it's רבי. Rabi. All right,
fine. So we could we tried to contradict you know to challenge
both positions, but obviously it wasn't clear because you can't prove whether
it was the position of רבי Rabi or the רבנן. Rabanan. Now
we continue. תנן המפריש חטאת ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה תמות. Tnan hamafrish
chatas ve'avda ve'hifrish acheres tachteya tamus. Okay, so that's the first line
of our משנה. Mishna. You separate out a חטאת, Chatas, you actually
brought number two, you find number one, it has to die. טעמא
דקרבה הא לא קרבה תרעה. Ta'ama d'karva ha lo karva tir'eh. Now
we're going to basically say you're trying to limit the רבנן's Rabanan
position. But the משנה Mishna sounds like the רבנן Rabanan are pretty
much don't agree to רבי Rabi at all. The משנה Mishna seems
like they absolutely reject רבי Rabi and here both of these approaches
try to say that there are many times the רבנן Rabanan agree
to רבי. Rabi. So that's now going to be challenged. So our
משנה Mishna says that the reason is that the only reason it
dies is because you brought it. If you didn't bring it, you
would let it graze. It sounds like under all circumstances if it
was found before the other one was brought. לא שנא נתכפר באבודה
ולא שנא נתכפר באינה אבודה. Lo shena niskaper ba'avuda velo shena niskaper
be'eina avuda. Doesn't matter whether you brought number one or number two.
לא שנא משך ולא שנא לא משך. Lo shena mashach velo shena
lo mashach. Doesn't matter if you selected on your own or you
didn't select on your own. The simple sense is that when you
find it before you brought number two, you never have to let
it die. תיובתא דתרוייהו. Tyufta detarvayehu. So it's a contradiction to both
of them. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מילתא דפסיקא ליה קתני
מילתא דלא פסיקא ליה לא קתני. Milta defsika lei kasni milta d'lo
psika lei lo kasni. No, what we need to say is if
you find number one after you bring number two, then you always
will number one will die. פסיקא ליה Psika lei meaning categorically, there
are no distinctions. If you find number one after you brought number
two, it will always die. If you find number one before you
brought number two... then it depends and we're not talking about that.
So you should not infer from the משנה Mishna that if it
was found earlier, it never dies. You should infer from the משנה
Mishna that if it's found earlier, sometimes it doesn't die, sometimes it
will. Okay.
No distinctions and no exceptions.
No exceptions, I guess I should say, right. תנן, Tnan, המפריש מעות
לחטאתו. hamafrish maos l'chataso. So now let's keep on going in the
משנה. Mishna. You set aside money. ואבדו והפריש אחרים תחתיהן. v'avdu v'hifrish
acherim tachtehen. You lost the money and you separated other money. ואחר
כך נמצאו המעות. v'achar kach nimtzu hamaos. יביא מאלו ומאלו. yavi me'elu
u'me'elu. So what's the way you solve it? You take from both
piles. חטאת Chatas והשאר יפלו לנדבה. v'hashar yiplu l'nedava. And therefore everything
left over is not considered rejected, it's left over and you use
it for an עולה. Olah. טעמא דמתכפר מאלו ומאלו. Taama d'miskaper me'elu
u'me'elu. So it sounds like, and we find that the only solution
is that you take from both piles. הא מאחד, Ha me'echad, if
you would take from only one pile, יוליכם לים המלח. yolichem l'Yam
Hamelach. You have to throw them into the Dead Sea. לא שנא
נתכפר באבודה ולא שנא נתכפר בשאינה אבודה. Lo shena miskaper b'avuda v'lo
shena miskaper b'she'eina avuda. ולא שנא משך ולא שנא לא משך. V'lo
shena mashach v'lo shena lo mashach. It sounds like, now again we're
assuming that this is going according to the חכמים, Chachamim, right? Before
we questioned whether it was going to the חכמים, Chachamim, but for
now we're assuming that even the middle section is going to the
חכמים. Chachamim. So it sounds like there's no solution other than mixing
the piles. But according to the חכמים, Chachamim, why is that? There
are solutions. You can ask בית דין, Beis Din, you can pick
the, you can use the one that was lost, number one, rather
than number two. So there are solutions here. תיובתא דרב פפא? Tiyuvta
d'Rav Pappa? So it's a contradiction? He says, הכא נמי מילתא דפסיקא
ליה קתני מילתא דלא פסיקא ליה לא קתני. Hacha nami milta d'psika
lei katani milta d'lo psika lei lo katani. Here too, we're not
looking to, we're looking to make an obvious solution. If you mix
the piles, you'll always solve it. If you don't mix the piles,
then it depends. Are you using pile number one or are you
using pile number two? Are you asking the רב? Rav? Are you
asking the בית דין? Beis Din? Or are you not asking the
בית דין? Beis Din? So therefore you should not infer from here
that there's no other solutions. It's just that this is a solution
that solves all the problems. There might be other solutions as well.
The easier answer of course is what the גמרא Gemara said before,
that this whole middle section is רבי. Rebbi. But here the גמרא
Gemara is assuming it works even according to the חכמים. Chachamim. אמר
רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. Okay, so now we have, so now
we have sort of wrapped that up for the time being, that
there are times where the חכמים Chachamim agree to רבי. Rebbi. If
you either bring number, bring number number two, they agree to רבי,
Rebbi, or if you select on your own, they agree to רבי.
Rebbi. Okay, because there are times that the חכמים Chachamim might agree
to רבי Rebbi even if it was found before. Now we're new,
introducing a new point. אמר רבי אמי, Amar Rabbi Ami, המפריש שני
ציבורי מעות לאחריות. hamafrish sheni tziburei maos l'achrayos. And this is what
I was sort of telling you at the beginning, that you need
something to be אבוד avud in order for it to be a
problem. If you start out with two things sanctified, you're not going
to say it has to die. One you bring and the other
will, you'll graze. So he describes that with the case of not
animals but money. You set aside two piles of money לאחריות, l'achrayos,
meaning that one should be for surety, collateral for the other as
it were, like if you lose one pile of money then you'll
use the other one. נתכפר באחד מהן
והשני יפלו לנדבה. Niskaper b'echad mehen v'hasheni yiplu l'nedava. So one you
use for a קרבן korban and the second one you use for
an עולה. Olah. It doesn't have the status of מתה mesa because
they're all designated from the beginning. So the גמרא Gemara says, אליבא
דמאן? aliba d'man? Who do you have to tell me this according
to? אילימא אליבא דרבי, Ilima aliba d'Rebbi, פשיטא דיפלו לנדבה. pshita d'yiplu
l'nedava. If you say רבי, Rebbi, then it's obvious. Why is it
obvious? עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אלא במקום שיש איבוד. Ad kan
lo ka'amar Rebbi ela b'makom sheyesh ibud. We explained, remember when we
explained רבי Rebbi why he says that it dies even when you
bring number one, it's because since number two was in place of
number one, it also has a quasi status of lost. But but
the way we framed it before, everybody agrees something needs the status
of איבוד, ibud, of lost, in order for it to be a
problem. Right? That's, that was your point, David, right? So even רבי
Rebbi when he says you found the dot dot dot, it's only
because there was something that was lost and that gave the replacement
a status of lost and therefore we said if you're atoned with
another one, then it has to die. But you need a status
of lost. Here nothing had a status of lost, so it's obvious
it's not a problem.
אבל לאחריות מודה. Aval l'achrayos modeh. If it was set aside not
because one of them was lost but just to be a backup,
he would agree that it that doesn't have to get thrown out
or die. ואלא אליבא דרבנן? V'ela aliba d'Rabanan? According to the רבנן,
Rabanan, that's even more obvious. Right? The רבנן Rabanan are more, are
more lenient about this. פשיטא ליה דיפלו לנדבה. Pshita lei d'yiplu l'nedava.
קל וחומר. Kal v'chomer. Obviously, it's a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. השתא
מפריש לאיבוד אמרו רבנן לאו כאיבוד דמי. Hashta mafrish l'ibud amru Rabanan
lav k'ibud dami. Even when something is in number two is designated
to to take place of number one, they don't give it a
quasi lost status. לאחריות מיבעיא? L'achrayos mibaya? Of course that if it's
designated from the very beginning as a backup, they're not going to
give it. So basically both רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabanan say
that something needs a quasi a lost status in order to be
מתה. mesa. And therefore this doesn't. Now of course you could say
maybe that's exactly what or no, that's exactly what he's clarifying. I
mean the גמרא Gemara before read that into רבי, Rebbi, but how
do we know that's רבי's Rebbi position? So maybe that's exactly what
he's clarifying, that רבי, Rebbi, even רבי's Rebbi position is based on
the fact that something was lost. But the גמרא Gemara thinks, takes
that for granted. So why do we need this חידוש? chiddush? We
should take that for granted. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואלא אליבא
דרבי שמעון איצטריכא ליה. v'ela aliba d'Rabbi Shimon itztricha lei. You need
this according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Now which is רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon? You might remember way back that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
was the one that emphasized that the חמש חטאות המתות chamesh chatas
amesos were all one group and that since therefore some of them
don't apply בציבור, b'tzibur, none of them apply בציבור. b'tzibur. So the
גמרא Gemara understands it wasn't at all clear from the earlier רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. But the גמרא Gemara understands that based on that,
we see that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically
really emphasizes that you always have this הלכה halacha of מיתה. meisa.
Now again, that wasn't really clear. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was really
just saying if it's, you know, if it's, you know, if it's
the whole group comes all together, if you have, if part of
the group doesn't apply, none of the group applies. But the גמרא
Gemara somehow translates into saying the flip, that when it does apply,
it's always מיתה, meisa, no exceptions, that he's even more מחמיר machmir
than רבי. Rebbi. So let's take a look.
So אליבא דרבי שמעון aliba d'Rabbi Shimon איצטריך ליה. itzterich lei. מהו
דתימא mahu d'teima מיתה לרבי שמעון meisa l'Rabbi Shimon היא גופא, hi
gufa, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says the same way he sort
of treats things as categorical, all five or none, he also says
always dies, never grazes, when you apply the הלכה halacha there are
no exceptions. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan דאית ליה d'is lei
נדבה. nedava. No, he allows for exceptions. The logic would still be
the same as we said, since you don't have something lost, but
it was necessary to clarify this according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
that even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees when there was nothing lost,
it's not a problem.
ומי אמרת umi amart דלית ליה d'leis lei נדבה? nedava? Now the
גמרא Gemara is really not letting up. Okay, that's a good point,
but I didn't need you to tell me that. I obviously knew
he held of cases where it didn't have to die. How did
I know that? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon והתניא vehatanya שלוש עשרה שופרות
shlosh esrei shofros היו במקדש. hayu b'mikdash. There were thirteen צדקה tzedaka
boxes essentially in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. The reason they say
שופרות shofros is because it had a very narrow opening at the
top and a very wide at the bottom, right, so that was,
you know, you put money in but you can't, right, you can't
take it out through the hole. Okay, anyway, והיה כתוב עליהן, vehaya
kasuv aleihen, so here's what was written on them. תקלין חדתין, taklin
chadatin, new שקלים, shekalim, basically if you didn't give your שקלים shekalim
for that year, there were times during the remainder of the year
that you could contribute still to the communal שקל shekel even if
you missed the original time you were supposed to give it, like
back in אדר. Adar. ועתיקין, ve'atikin, and old שקלים, shekalim, if you
actually had missed for giving last year's, you could still give now
and they would use it the same thing they would do with
leftover funds that they had from last year. The question in all
this is how does the קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur work for you,
but you know, basically when they buy something, they buy it for
the sake of the ציבור tzibbur even if you were not one
of the, you didn't contribute on a timely basis. So this year's
שקלים, shekalim, last year's שקלים shekalim that you're a little late, you're
making it up.
קינין וגוזלי עולה, kinin vegozlei ola, birds and, you know,
other עולות, olos, whatever, קינין וגוזלי עולות kinin vegozlei olos are different
types of birds basically. And this is basic, קינין, kinin, excuse me,
those are two. קינין kinin is pairs of birds that had to
be brought for קרבנות korbanos particularly for people like a זב zav
and a זבה zava and a יולדת yoledes and a מצורע. metzora.
So interestingly, to sort of make things more efficient, the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash they didn't require that you bring the birds and then
you stand there with your קרבן, korban, you just put the money
in and they made sure to take care of it on a
daily basis. And you would know by the end of the day
that they had used the money and that they had brought the
קרבן. korban. I assume that they had to close off that, those
contributions a few hours before the business day ended so they would
have time to use it. But anyways, that's קינין, kinin, those are
bird sacrifices that were used for like a זב zav and a
יולדת. yoledes. וגוזלי עולה vegozlei ola is just somebody that had given
a קרבן עולה korban ola of birds, which apparently was a common
קרבן korban because it was not so expensive, you would just put
the money in there and they would take care of it. Again,
it's a little bit funny, קינין וגוזלי עולה.
kinin
vegozlei ola.
No, and also קינין, kinin, yeah, קינין kinin are one's a חטאת
chatas and it's for מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kapara, so this is just
an עולה. ola. But you know, what is a little disturbing about
this, I must admit, is the fact that it depersonalizes it, it's
all about now you're giving of your קרבן korban is just putting
money in a box, you know, and what does it mean now
that I'm giving a קרבן korban of a bird if all it
translates into is a certain amount of money into a box?
You don't bring your own bird?
You can, but this was a way to make it convenient for
people who didn't want to. Okay,
now we're going on. עצים ולבונה, eitzim ulevona, זהב לכפורת, zahav lakapores,
and you could also another thing that if you wanted to contribute
towards wood for the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or for frankincense or
for gold for the כפורת, kapores, which is an interesting phrase what
that means, for the
כפורת. kapores. So רש"י Rashi says maybe it means for certain vessels,
gold vessels. Anyway, those were seven of them. You can count.
That's just an example, you could have brought any other spice, right?
No, no, no, לבונה levona you would bring on a daily basis.
Oh, not לבונה levona for קטורת ketores or something like that or
whatever?
No, no, no, you would be מנדב לבונה menadev levona for the
מנחה mincha offerings or not for like לחם הפנים lechem hapanim or
something.
No, no, no, no, no, just you can bring your own נדבה,
nedava, you know, לבונה levona as a
קרבן נדבה. korban nedava. Okay. וששה לנדבה, veshisha linedava, six for נדבה.
nedava. What does נדבה nedava mean? It means our cases of when
a חטאת chatas has to graze and you left, you know, the
money we said, what happens with an אשם asham or חטאת chatas
when an אשם asham can't be used or, you know, חטאת chatas
doesn't die, the cases when a חטאת chatas doesn't die, we say
the money goes for a נדבה. nedava. And for נדבה nedava we
said meant a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, an עולת ציבור. olas tzibbur.
So where would you put that money? You had this case of
a חטאת chatas that based on when it was found, whatever, it
doesn't have to die, you transfer it to money and you put
the money into one of these six boxes. Or you had an
אשם asham that if it were חטאת chatas it would have died,
but because it's an אשם asham it becomes a נדבה, nedava, you
put it to the money, the money you put in these boxes.
Why do you need six for נדבה? nedava?
Apparently, that's, isn't that surprising? Apparently, this happened a lot, which is
pretty shocking. Anyway,
ותני עלה, vesani ala, ששה לנדבה, shisha linedava, we explained that. What
does that mean? עולה הבאה מן המותרות ola haba min hamotorot that's
an עולה ola that comes from leftover money from a חטאת chatas
or an אשם asham שאין עורה לכהנים she'ein ora la-kohanim דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei rabbi yehuda. Rabbi Yehuda says that what there's a special
הלכה halacha although before we said when you bring this עולת ציבור
olat tzibur because of this money from a חטאת chatas and an
אשם asham that the כהנים kohanim get the skin, here Rabbi Yehuda
says that there's a special הלכה halacha that the כהנים kohanim can't
benefit from it. It has to go all to the בית המקדש.
beit hamikdash. Now how does it go all to the בית המקדש?
beit hamikdash? The meat gets burnt but you don't burn skin on
a מזבח. mizbe'ach. So you sell the skin and with the proceeds
you buy another עולה, ola, right? And you keep on it's sort
of like you know what is that
called? Charlie, infinite loop? Not an infinite loop but you keep on
selling so that you know more and more and more at the
end you're going to be left with one skin that you can't
do anything with. But anyway that's what he says, that's the special
הלכה halacha that you can't the כהנים kohanim don't get the skin.
אמר ליה רב נחמיה amar lei rav nechemya ואמרי לה רבי שמעון
ve-amrei lah rabbi shimon Rav Nechemya and some say Rabbi Shimon and
that's why we're quoting it because it's Rabbi Shimon said to him
אם כן בטלה מדרשו של יהוידע הכהן im ken batla midrasho shel
yehoyada ha-kohen then you have to throw out this מדרש midrash of
this famous מדרש midrash of יהוידע. yehoyada. דתניא זה מדרש דרש יהוידע
הכהן de-tanya zeh midrash darash yehoyada ha-kohen אשם הוא אשם אשם להשם.
asham hu asham asham la-hashem. So meaning it's an אשם, asham, it's
an אשם asham to God. Some goes to God and some goes
to the כהנים. kohanim. יכול להביא כל דבר הבא מן
המותרות... yakhol le-havi kol davar ha-ba min ha-motorot... I'm
sorry... וכולו... ve-khulo... I'm going to take the גרסא girsa וכולו. ve-khulo.
Anyway,
להביא כל דבר הבא ממותרי חטאות ואשמות le-havi kol davar ha-ba mi-motrei
chataot va-ashamot this teaches you that any money funds that were used
from חטאות chataot and אשמות ashamot ליקח בהם עולות likach bahem olot
that you buy an עולה, ola, that's what you do with this
leftover money from חטאת chatas and אשם. asham. הבשר לשם ha-basar la-shem
that's אשם אשם להשם, asham asham la-hashem, the meat goes to God
והעור לכהנים ve-ha-or la-kohanim and the skin to the כהנים. kohanim. So
that's a debate of what do you do with these special עולות
נדבה. olot nedava. But the point for us is who says it?
רבי שמעון rabbi shimon says it. So you see רבי שמעון rabbi
shimon acknowledges that there are cases with leftover money for a חטאת
chatas that goes for an עולה. ola. And when we said you
designated two piles as a חטאת, chatas, we're saying that how is
that different than what's the case of leftover money? Leftover money is
the simplest. I designate five hundred dollars for a חטאת chatas and
it only costs me four hundred. So the leftover, the hundred, that
goes for an עולה. ola. So that's the case we're talking about
here. We're assuming now that if I have two piles of money,
I'll bring it from one, the other pile is backup, it's the
same as if I had one pile and there was leftover. So
if רבי שמעון rabbi shimon agrees with leftover from one pile, presumably
he would also agree from if there's an unused pile. הגמרא ha-gemara
says לא נצרכא lo nitzrekha not necessarily. איצטריך itzterikh I need it
to tell me סלקא דעתך אמינא salka datakh amina כי אית ליה
נדבה לרבי שמעון בחטאת חדא ki it lei nedava le-rabbi shimon be-chatat
chada when does he hold that the money goes for an עולה
ola when it's one thing, one category, meaning leftover money from one
pile. אבל בתרתי לא aval be-tartei lo if you had two piles,
maybe the second pile gets designated as the rejected one and it's
like a חטאת מתה chatat meta קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
that he doesn't say that. So what we actually learn here is
a very important point that I've been telling you all along and
the גמרא gemara takes for obvious but it's not obvious at all.
The whole principle of חטאת מתה chatat meta builds on the fact
of נתכפר באחר nitkapar be-acher builds on the fact that it was
אבוד. avud. So even Rebbe who says that it doesn't matter which
one you bring, because the second one because it relates to the
first one also has a quasi-אבוד avud status. But when it doesn't
have an אבוד avud status, even if you were נתכפר nitkapar with
one and not with the other, then it's not מתה meta but
the money goes for an עולה. ola.